Hi, everybody. Welcome to the last lecture
of 6 .006. Last lecture, we talked about
summing up this class and talking about
future courses in the department that use
this material. Just as a pointer to some of
those classes, I have a little slide here
I didn't get to at the last lecture,
talking about kind of what I was talking
about at the end of last lecture, about
different models, different specialized
classes on different aspects of 006
material. For example, more graph stuff,
different models of computation,
randomness, complexity. All of these things
have their own specialized classes
in the department, as well as a lot of
applications for this material in
subjects like biology, cryptography, and in
particular for your instructors, the realm
of graphics and geometry. So all of your
instructors this term happen to be
geometers and be interested in geometry
-related problems. Me in particular, I
didn't start out in computer science. I
started out in mechanical engineering. And
the thing that was my passion coming into
MIT was origami. And so here's a couple of
pieces that I designed, origami pieces, one
square sheet of paper without cutting.
Here's a lobster. And here's a copyrighted
dinosaur from a
particular movie.
Kind of hook me up with origami models, as
an origami artist and design these things
by using some of those algorithmic
techniques. It wasn't until grad school as
a mechanical engineer that I started
talking with our other instructor here,
Professor Domaine, about using algorithms
in computer science to design not just
origami, which we both do, but also folded
structures that can be used for mechanical
applications like space flight,
deployable bridges in times when you need
a temporary bridge or shelter or something
like that, deployable structures where
you might need to make folded structures,
transformable structures that can
have different applications for different
purposes, need to reconfigure. The dream
being that we have these powerful devices
in our pockets right now, cell phones,
which are really powerful because we can
reconfigure the bits in them to make
software of all different kinds. There's an
exponential number of different programs
that we can write, and that's part of why
you're here is to write the next best one.
So that's how to make kind of a universal
device at the electronic level. What if we
could do that from a material standpoint?
What if I could reprogram the matter in
my phone so that not only could I reprogram
the app that's on your phone, but instead
of having, say, the iPhone X or whatever
that you have and you want to go buy the
iPhone 11, instead you download a software
app that then reconfigures the matter in
your phone. It folds or reconfigures into
the next generation iPhone. You don't
have to throw away that old one. You can
essentially recycle the material that
you have to potentially save material, save
cost, and be better for the environment
potentially. So I started moving into
computer science because I found that it
was a really good way to model the world
and solve some really interesting problems
about folding that I really enjoyed. So the
three of us today are going to spend some
time talking a little bit about how we can
use algorithms, 6 .006 material and beyond,
in our own research. And we're going to
start off with Professor Demain
and then Professor Solomon.
Demain's geometric folding algorithms
is sort of a broader umbrella for folding
-related things, which is encapsulated by
this class 6 .849, which is happening next
fall. So you should all take it. 006
should be a reasonable background. And in
general, we're interested in two kinds of
problems. The big one is origami design or,
in general, folding design, where you have
some specifications of what you'd like to
build. In this case, I wanted to make a
logo for 6849. And I imagined extruding
that text into third dimension. And then I
wanted an algorithm to tell me how to fold
that structure. And so there is an
algorithm, which I'll talk about in a
moment, that gives you a crease pattern.
And then currently, you fold it by hand.
The dream is we'll eventually have folding
machines that do it all for us. And so
that's the origami design, where you go
from the target shape back to the crease
pattern. The reverse direction is sort of
foldability. If I gave you a structure like
this and I wanted to know, does it fold,
that's a problem we call foldability in
general, a class of problems. And sadly,
most of those problems are NP -hard. Jason
and I proved that foldability is hard for a
general, given a crease pattern like that,
telling you whether it folds into anything.
It turns out to be NP -hard. So that's bad
news. So we focus a lot on the design
problem, because that actually tends to be
easier. We can solve it with
algorithms like that one you're seeing.
And so a long time ago, we proved that you
can fold everything. If I give you a square
piece of paper and you take any polygon you
want to make, or maybe the paper is white
on one side, black on the other, you
want to fold some two -color pattern like a
zebra, or in general, some three
-dimensional surface like these guys, there
is a way to fold it from a large enough
square paper. And it's actually really easy
to prove that with an algorithm. I have the
sketch of the two pages of proof that we
go over in 6849, but I'll just hand wave
a little bit. If you take a piece of paper,
like my lecture notes here, the first thing
you do is fold it down into a very long,
narrow strip, much longer and narrower than
this one, wasting most of the material.
And then you take your strip, and you just
figure out how to turn it. And then you
just sort of zigzag back and forth along
the surface. So it's very cool in that you
can prove with an algorithm and in a very
short amount of time to someone you can
actually fold everything. Of course, it's
a terrible folding, because in the very
first step, we throw away all but epsilon
of the material. But it's a starting point.
And then that was back in the late 90s,
one of the first results in computational
origami. And in modern times, we look for
better algorithms that are more efficient,
that try to minimize the scale factor from
how big of a piece of paper do I start from
to how big of a model do I get. And one of
the cool ways these days, which is invented
by Tomohiro Itachi and then analyzed by the
two of us, is called Orgamizer. It's free
software. You take a 3D model, and it makes
it into a crease pattern that you fold
from a square. In this case, it uses 22 %
of the area, which is pretty good, similar
to these guys in terms of efficiency, but
very different kind of folding than what
you would get from more traditional origami
design, which uses different algorithms,
which I'm not going to talk about. But
you should take the class. Jason gives a
lecture in the class that you can learn
from him. But the vision is we can take any
sheet of material that can hold a crease,
like this sheet of steel that Tomohiro is
folding. It was cut by a big laser cutter
at MIT. And this is him in the Stata Center
several years ago folding it.
And so this is like a totally new way to
manufacture 3D objects. And you can make
particularly interesting objects that
either collapse flat for transportation or
transform, like Jason was talking about.
But I'm just giving you a flavor. I think
the first paper we wrote together was
on maze folding. So this is an example of
folding a maze from
a rectangle of paper.
Try this out. You just Google for our maze
folder. You can generate a random maze. And
this 3D structure can be folded from this
crease pattern. That's a really hard one.
So maybe try something smaller. You can
also write your favorite message and fold
this maze extruded graph from this crease
pattern. You might want to start with
something smaller.
And it's actually quite easy to prove this
algorithmically if you have a really good
org, obviously, like Jason on your team.
What you do is design how to fold each type
of vertex. This is just a graph on a grid.
So there are some constant number of
different ways that each vertex could look.
It could be degree 4. It could be degree
3. There's a T. It could be degree 2,
either as a turn or a straight. And you
design little gadgets, little crease
patterns that fold into each of those
little structures. And if you can do it in
a way that these boundaries are compatible,
then to fold the whole thing, you just sort
of glue together those crease patterns.
And that's how that software works. And
so this is particularly interesting because
you can fold an arbitrarily complicated
maze, m by n, with a constant scale factor.
As long as the height that you're extruding
that maze is constant, then this is one
family of shapes we know how to fold
really well. In general, we're trying to
understand what makes this lobster a nice
shape in that it can be represented with a
not too large piece of paper. And we don't
have general answers to that problem. I
think that was a whirlwind tour of
computational origami. I also play a lot in
algorithmic sculpture. One of the leading
edges in origami and origami math is
understanding how curved creases work.
And one of our favorite models is this one,
where you fold concentric circles,
alternating mountain and valley, cut a
circular hole, and it folds into this
kind of Pringle shape as a nice physics
equilibrium thing. And then you can turn
it into fun sculptures like this. These are
done with my dad, Martin Demaine, who's
also here at MIT, or this guy. This paper
has been printed with a pattern according
to getting burned by glass. And then it
gets folded and then put inside glass, also
made here at MIT. And so we use sculpture
to try to explore and understand
intuitively how curved creases work. And
then we get better and better understanding
of the mathematics of even we don't even
know whether this surface exists, whether
it's possible to fold in this way, although
getting close to proving it.
So that was sort of in the top level of
this hierarchy. Computational geometry is a
bigger umbrella, which is represented
by another class, 6850, that's being taught
this term.
Geometric folding within that branch. Let
me briefly tell you about another world of
geometry, very different in terms of model
of computation. Oh, I jumped ahead a little
bit. Rewind. Let me show you one
more fun demo, which if I find my scissors.
So if I take a rectangle of paper and I
fold it flat and make one straight cut,
what shapes can I get? This is called the
folding cut problem. It's hundreds of years
old. Here, for
example, I get a swan.
Here I get one
straight cut. I unfold and get an
angelfish. Tough audience today. I keep
going. I've seen all these before. This one
is a particularly difficult one to fold.
Only fold. And to cut, yeah.
OK. Hopefully that works well.
This is the MIT logo. Ooh, ah. Yeah.
Go MIT. All right. So that's actually the
first problem I worked on in computational
origami. It's a lot of fun. And there's a
really interesting algorithm here also for
computing the crease pattern, how to fold
your piece of paper to align. In fact, any
graph you draw on a piece of paper, you can
align all those edges and nothing else.
So you cut along the line, you get exactly
what you want. Cool. All right. Now I
want to talk about something completely
different, which is self -assembly. A fun
thing you can do with DNA, which we all
have, just pick out some cool DNA strands
and design them in a clever way so they fit
together to form a kind of square with
dangling ends, which I'll call glues. And
each of those dangling ends can have a very
particular pattern. And only identical or
complementary patterns will attach to each
other. And so you can use this to design
your own self -assembling system, like
biology does but engineered, for example,
to build a computer. This is an example
of taking a bunch of these square tiles and
building a binary counter. This thing
is roughly counting in binary along the
diagonal. It's a little skewed, so it's
hard to see. But the general model is you
have squares. This is sort of the
computational model with four different
glues. And you can build any square you
want, but you don't have very many of these
different glues. Ideally. And then if you
have two tiles with complementary glues,
they'll want to match together. But it
depends how strong this glue is, how much
affinity there is for how long those DNA
dangling ends are, and also the temperature
of your system. If you have really high
temperature, nothing will stick together.
Low temperature, things will stick together
even if they're not supposed to. And so if
you tune your system really well, you can
design a system so that maybe these glues
are really strong. And so let's write E
here, Eric. And so these tiles will always
glue together. But only when all three
of these are glued together can this tile,
which has C complement and F complement,
then it will, if you set the temperatures
just right, only because both of these
edges match will this tile be able to come
in. And that's the basis for that, building
that binary counter. And so this is a very
different model of computation from
what we're used to in this class, where you
think of instructions and they run one at
a time. Here, the model of computation is
geometric. It's these squares that are just
floating around and gluing together. And
so your program at any moment is
some conglomerate of squares. And so I just
wanted to mention it because it's a really
fun model. You can prove cool things in
this model, like how to build any shape by
a sequence of pores, mixings between tiles
that you can execute in parallel. And so it
only takes log n time in parallel steps, a
linear number of different mix operations
to make an arbitrary shape, even using a
constant number of different glues, which
is cool and maybe practical. You can also
use it to build a replicator, where you're
given an object like this that you don't
know the shape of. Like, we don't know
whether this exists. And we can't model it
mathematically very well. And you would
stick it in a vat. And all these tiles
would attach and basically build a mold and
then start photocopying in 3D that mold.
And you can build that with a system with
only two steps, I believe, and a constant
number of tile types. And it does all
of that in this model in constant time. In
reality, you'd have to feed this machine
and wait for it to print out all these
things. And these experiments take hours,
if not days, to run. In theory, it's really
cool. And you get some really fun models
and very general results. You can also use
it to build a miniaturizer or a magnifier
and other fun stuff. OK. So that was a
brief tour of computational geometry.
I work mostly in four different areas of
algorithms, geometry, data structures,
graph algorithms, and what I call
recreational algorithms. I think I
made up that term. And let's go into data
structures, which is represented by
this class 6 .8 .5 .1. All of the classes I
mentioned have online video lectures. So
especially for those watching at home on
OpenCourseWare, most of these classes are
on OpenCourseWare. And if not, they're on
my web page. So 6 .8 .5 .1, Advanced Data
Structures, is an extension of the sorts of
data structures you've seen here in 006 and
the ones you will see in 6046. I thought
I'd give you a flavor
of one such result.
Which is a
problem we've seen in this class done
better. So suppose you want to store a
dynamic ordered set.
So this is the set interface. Dynamic in
the sense that I have insert and delete.
And ordered in the sense that I want
to support find next and finds previous.
So exactly which subset of the set
interface you choose influences what data
structure you've seen. We've seen for
dynamic sets, you want to use hashing. If
you don't care about find next, if you just
care about find, then hashing is great,
constant expected. You can prove stronger
things about hashing than we do in that
class. But if you want dynamic and ordered,
you cannot do constant time for operation.
You can prove that, which is cool. And
so what data structure have we seen that
solves this problem pretty well? Set AVL.
Set AVL trees, which solve everything in
log n. So log n
is one competitor.
Yeah. I'm interested in this
in the word RAM model, which
is the only model we've seen in this
class. This happens to work in the stronger
model. And we can do better than log n in
the following. It'll take me a while before
I get better. But here's at least a
different bound we can get. Log w. This is
via a structure
called van Emde Boas,
who's a person. AVL is two people. Van
Emde Boas, I've actually met. So log w.
Remember, w is our word size. So this is a
bit of a weird running time. It's great if
w is like log n. Then this is log log n.
And we know w is at least log n, but it
could be bigger. We don't really have a
sense of how big w could get. Maybe it's
even n. Maybe it's big. It's the same.
Maybe it's bigger than n. And then this is
maybe worse. But for most w's, this is
actually pretty good and indeed optimal.
But it's not strictly better in any sense
yet. On the other hand, there's another
data structure which runs in log n divided
by log w. This is called fusion trees. This
was invented around the time that cold
fusion was in the news. And so they wanted
data structures to represent. And so we can
achieve this bound, or we can achieve this
bound. And this bound is good if w is
large. This bound is good if w is small.
And so you can always take the min of the
two, whatever is better. And in particular,
the min
of those two things is at most, I think
it's square root log n over log log n. If
you want a bound just in terms of n, then
the crossover point between these two is
this place. And so you're always at most
this, which is quite a bit better than the
log n of a v l. We've got a square
root, and we've got a slight thing in the
denominator, pretty tiny. But the big thing
is the square root. And that's kind of
cool. And it turns out that's pretty much
optimal. In terms of an n bound, this is
optimal. One of these two in general is
roughly optimal up to log log terms. For
fun, I threw up the actual formula for the
right bound, which is tight up to constant
factors. There's matching upper and lower
bounds, which we talk about. It's min of
three things, four things, including log
of w over a divided by log of log w over a
over log of log n over a. So that's
the last term that I just read. It's messy.
Surprisingly, that is the right answer
for this very particular problem, a very
natural problem. What is a? A is the
log of the space you're using. So it's the
address size. Good question. If you have
a polynomial space data structure, then
basically these are optimal. And this is
generalizing to beyond that. Maybe you have
a little bit more than polynomial space.
Cool. So that's data structures. I'm going
to jump ahead to graph algorithms, which if
you want to take this class, I recommend a
time travel device. Go back to fall 2011.
It may never get taught again. But it has
videos. So you can watch, instead of time
traveling, if you don't want to watch it
live, you can just watch the recorded
version. It was taught by a bunch of
postdocs that were here and a bit myself.
And so what I like to do with graphs is the
world of planar graphs
or near planar graphs.
So we've talked a lot about this class for
algorithms that work for arbitrary graphs.
And the algorithms we've seen in this class
are pretty much the best we know for a lot
of problems for arbitrary graphs. But if
your graph has some structure, like it's a
road network and there aren't too many
overpasses, you can usually draw these
graphs in the plane without crossings.
That's the meaning of planar. Maybe not
exactly. Maybe just a few crossings.
There's a generalization of this, which I
won't get into. But let's just think about
planar graphs. Planar graphs have some nice
features, like they always have a linear
number of edges. They're always sparse.
So you can immediately plug that into our
existing bounds. But even so, Dijkstra in
such a graph would take v log v time. For
planar graphs, you can do the equivalent of
Dijkstra, meaning I can compute single
source shortest paths with non -negative
edge weights in linear time.
No log. OK? Not that impressive, but remove
a log. More impressive is we can do the
equivalent of Bellman -Ford, which is
single source shortest paths with arbitrary
edge weights in
a planar graph in
some time. Almost linear time.
v log squared v over log log v. So there's
a couple of log factors here. But for the
almost linear time, whereas Bellman -Ford
would take v squared time. So this is a
huge improvement over what we've seen
in the class. These are quite complicated
algorithms, but they're covered in that
class if you're interested in them. Then
the area I work in a lot is approximation
algorithms for planar graphs. And let me
just give you a fun flavor using something
we know, which is breadth -first search.
So breadth -first search you can think
of as building these sort of rings around a
single root node. And there's this general
approach, as introduced by Baker in 1994,
we've used for lots of different problems.
You want to solve some NP -hard problem on
a graph. So just run breadth -first search
from an arbitrary vertex and decompose your
graph into these layers. You could
number them. 0, 1, 2, 3. These are levels.
And let's just delete some of those layers.
Let's say let's delete every fourth layer.
So maybe I delete this one. I delete
all the vertices in that layer. And then I
delete all the things in layer 8 and layer
12 and so on. I don't know which one to
start with. But I'll just try them all.
And then I delete every fourth layer after
that. So I've deleted, on average, about a
quarter of the graph. And it turns out, for
a lot of problems that you care about, like
choosing where to place fire stations in
this graph to minimize travel time for
if there's a fire somewhere in the graph.
Happens, fires and graphs. Then this will
only hurt your solution by a factor of 1
plus 1 quarter. So you'll get a solution
that's within 25 % of the optimal for a lot
of problems.
And that works for any value of 4. So I
could do it for 10. And then I'd get within
10 % of the optimal solution. But how do
I actually solve the problem once I delete
every fourth layer? Well, then your graph
has this extra special structure, which is
a constant number of layers, let's say, a
constant number of breadth -first search
layers. If you just look at this portion,
this connected component, or this connected
component in here, your graph is almost
like a cycle. It's like four cycles stacked
up together with some connections between
them. And it turns out that's something you
can solve with very fancy dynamic
programming, like the stuff we've seen in
this class, which focuses on just a single
path or a single cycle. But constant number
cycles, with more work, you can still do
everything in polynomial time. And so this
is a very general approach for getting
arbitrarily good approximation algorithms.
We call these 1 plus epsilon approximation
for any epsilon. But the larger the
epsilon, the more time you take. It's
something like 2 to the order 1 over
epsilon times polynomial n. So as long
as epsilon's constant, this is polynomial
time. It's called a p -test.
Anyway, that was graph algorithms. Last
topic is recreational algorithms, which is
maybe best encompassed by this class. 6892
is its latest name. It changes names every
once in a while. And I mentioned it in the
hardness complexity lecture, because this
class is all about hardness proofs
analyzing fun games and puzzles. We saw the
Tetris NP -hardness in that lecture. But
you can also prove Super Mario Brothers is
hard, or Portal is hard, or Mario Kart is
hard. Or The Witness, a modern video game,
is hard. Or one of our latest results is
that Recursed, that game in the top right,
is undecidable. There's no algorithm to
play that game perfectly. And you can even
download the level, an example
of the level, and play it if you dare.
So we have a lot of fun in that world of
hardness of different games and puzzles.
Where do I want to go next? OK, next topic
is balloon twisting. Totally different.
This is recreational, but not about
hardness. So this is an octahedron twisted
from one balloon. I made another one on
a stick. And so each of these is made from
one balloon. What graphs can you make
from one balloon? Well, you should read our
paper. And you can characterize how many
balloons you need to make each polyhedron.
And some of these problems
are NP -hard. And it's a lot of fun.
Cool. I think that's the end of the slides.
The last thing I wanted to show you is a
problem, a puzzle slash magic trick. It
comes from the puzzle world called the
picture hanging problem. So imagine you
have a picture. You want to hang it on a
wall. So you invest it in some nice rope.
And you hang it. And then on a nail, if the
nail falls out, the picture falls in your
set. So you invest in two nails, like I
have here. And maybe you hang your picture
on both those nails. Now, if one of the
nails falls out, you still have a crookedly
hung picture. The other nail falls out.
OK, it's gone. I want to hang a picture
on two nails such that if I remove either
nail, the picture falls. So Jason, pick a
nail, left or right? Left. Left, we remove.
And make sure this doesn't fall off. And
boom, the picture falls. Same wrapping. You
can check. You can rewind the video. Make
sure I did the same wrapping. And take out
the right one. Take out the right one. Good
choice. Then also the picture falls. And
so this is a classic puzzle. But you can
generalize it. So let me do it for three
nails, which is all I have here. This
nail's sagging a little bit. Y inverse, X
inverse. OK. I think that's right. So
this is one way to hang a picture on three
nails, such that if I remove any of the
nails, picture falls. Justin, one, two, or
three? Two. OK. Yeah, I want to get out of
the way and make sure I don't go over the
edge here. Yeah. It's a lot easier to
make this one work. But you can see, boom,
picture falls there. And of course, imagine
infinite gravity. And the picture falls.
And so you can generalize this to do
essentially any, it's called a monotone
Boolean function on any set of nails. You
can make any subset of the nails cause the
picture to fall and any collection
of subsets of nails to make it fall. Of
course, if you remove more nails, it's
still going to fall. That's the monotone
sense. But otherwise, you can do an
arbitrary pattern, which is fun. That's
actually a result with Ron Rivest and
a bunch of other people. I think I'm
approximately on time. So that was a
quick tour. And there are obviously various
classes here you can take. 6 .8 .9 .2,
the hardness class, was just offered last
semester. So it probably won't be for a
while. All these classes are online. Watch
the videos. Feel free to ask me questions.
And now we have Justin. I left you space
here for your outline.
You don't have to.
But I'll put your
name up. Thank you.
So Justin is also a geometer. Yeah, we've
got a lot of geometry people in 006 this
semester. Thank you. Okay. You know, it's
like, I can't help but share that on our
instructor chat, Eric was texting that he
was going to be, he was somehow nervous
that the applied guy would have all
the cool stuff to show off. And now I feel
totally boring.
Right. Yeah. So yeah, we have three
different geometry instructors in this
class. We have many different flavors of
geometry that are kind of represented in
this room here, from mechanical engineering
to theory, plus lots of other cool stuff
to whatever it is that I do. So I'm a
professor also. And I'm also the head of
the geometry department at CSIL. And I lead
a group that studies slightly more applied
geometry problems in some sense here at
CSIL. We kind of cross a lot of boundaries,
actually, closer to the math department
than to the theory group in computer
science, which I would argue is largely
a historical artifact rather than anything
interesting about computer science or math.
So continuing in our whirlwind tour of
interesting geometry
classes here at MIT,
I'm going to add to the list and we'll
introduce some of the ideas in the next
couple of slides here. So normally
every fall, I teach 6837, which is the
introduction to computer graphics course.
In fact, my background was working in an
animation studio for a little bit of time
and got one movie credit out of it until
they changed the standards for movie
credits and then that stopped happening.
But in any event, if you watch What's That
Movie Up with the old man, if you hit pause
at just the right moment, you can find me
right above the list of babies. That were
born during production. But in any event,
although computer graphics might not sound
like an algorithmic discipline, I'll try to
convince you guys that in some sense, you
could take just about anybody in our
department, have them teach 6706 and give a
similar talk that the material that you've
encountered in this course is going to be
relevant to your life. The other course
that I teach that might be of interest and
actually is a little more theoretically
flavored that I teach is 6838. So since
Eric so kindly put my name on the board
here, I guess I can draw a picture. So the
main object of interest in 6838 is
a particular thing called a simplicial
complex.
So usually in 6 .006, we spend a lot of
time thinking about graphs. So let me draw
you a graph. So I'm going to take a square
and subdivide it. And now let's say I put
edges diagonally. Like that.
Now, the thing is a bunch of nodes
can connect to my edges. In fact, if I took
this edge and I moved it down or something,
it would be the same graph. But of course,
in a lot of computer graphics applications,
this thing also looks an awful lot like a
square. And the reason is that, of course,
the graph here contains triangles inside of
it. And so for instance, maybe I think
of my graph as a collection of vertices, a
collection of edges. This is the sort of
notation we've seen before. And then I add
a third thing to my description, which is a
set of triplets. That's a set of triangles
here. And we can take a lot of the
algorithms that we've talked about in this
class and extend it to this case. So for
example, here's a deceptively annoying one.
Let's say that I want the shortest path
between two vertices of my graph. So we
certainly have learned Dijkstra's algorithm
as one technique to do that. And indeed,
common practice in computer graphics, which
is shameful, is on your triangle mesh, if
you want the shortest path between two
vertices, run Dijkstra's algorithm on the
edges. And let's see if that works
really quick. So let's say that I want the
shortest path between. And by the way, I'm
going to assume the lengths of my edges are
like the length as I've drawn them on the
board here. So it's like 1, 1 square root
of 2. OK. So let's say I want the shortest
path between the bottom left and the upper
right. For run Dijkstra's algorithm, we're
in good shape, right? I'll let you do the
computations at home. You'll get the
path that is these two edges. But here's a
really annoying thing. Let's say instead I
wanted the shortest path from the upper
left to the lower right. If I run
Dijkstra's algorithm on this triangulated
square, what's going to be the shortest
path? Yeah, in fact, there's a bunch of
them. One of them might go all the way down
and then all the way to the right. What's
the length of this path? 1, 2, 3, 4. Is
that the length of the shortest path? Well,
probably not. Well, we'd like our shortest
path to do something like that. But graphs
don't know how to talk to triangles. And
this is going to be a problem. In fact, it
wasn't until with history terms that we
were able to work out the correct algorithm
for a shortest path on a triangulated
domain like this. And that's the runtime
that we would expect. This is called
MMP. I'm guessing Eric and Jason could do a
better job describing it than I can.
But the basic idea of the MMP algorithm
actually really happens to be a nice
extension of the way that we taught
Dijkstra's algorithm in 6 .006 because they
really do keep track of these level sets
of the distance function. But now the level
sets have to window an edge like that when
I compute shortest path, which is a giant
headache. This is one of these algorithms
that was known in theory about 10 years
before anybody bothered to implement it in
a way that they could convince themselves
really ran in n log n time. And nowadays,
there's a cottage industry in computer
graphics research papers to implement this
and then speed it up in different ways.
And sadly, the reality is that a different
algorithm we cover in 6 .838 called fast
marching, which doesn't actually give you
the shortest path, but some approximation
thereof is faster, easier to use, and
basically indistinguishable. So in
any event, in 6 .838, we kind of have an
interesting dual mindset. On the one hand,
we'll talk about a lot of algorithms that
look like what we've done in whatever this
class is, 6 .006. But at the same time,
start to have a more geometric flavor.
And we don't worry quite as much about
integers. So in our computation model,
oftentimes we're kind of OK with real
numbers because that's not where the
headache is. And of course, when you write
your code in this class, you use double
precision floating point. If you're more
responsible, like in Jason's previous
lecture, you should probably keep track of
the number of operations and make sure that
your error is bounded. I'm not sure that
we really bother with that. In any
event, this allows us to kind of have two
different mindsets. There's one mindset
which is discrete. There's another mindset
which is smooth. So we think about
understanding geometry, like these
triangulated domains, as an approximation
of a smooth surface. And then we might want
to do stuff like compute curvature
and so on, which is really associated with
computing derivatives, which, of course,
we don't have on these kinds of simple
objects. And that leads to this really fun
area of math, computer science, whatever,
called discrete differential geometry,
which sounds like a contradiction in terms.
And it's something that we cover in quite
some detail in this course. So we build up
all of calculus. And the only calculations
you're allowed to do are on the vertices,
edges, and triangles of a triangle
mesh and get pretty far, including some
constructions of topology, like the Dirac
complex and so on. I would argue, actually,
if you take our course and then the
differential geometry course in the math
department, somehow some of the indices and
headaches that you often encounter in that
world are much more concrete when you try
to make them work on a mesh. In any event,
I think I've already spent all of my time.
I can tell you a little bit about research
in our group. So I lead kind of a weird,
extremely broad group where some of our
students are essentially theory students.
Put your keyboard. I'm sorry. It was a
reflex. But it was fast. All right. So we
have some students whose background is in
math, other ones that were in autonomous
driving. This three decided to come back
and work in research. And so because of
that, we have this extremely broad set of
research problems. Everything from the sort
of classic machine learning problems you
might encounter in geometry world, like
if I have a self -driving car and I want to
identify pedestrians and other cars on the
road in an efficient and accurate fashion.
By the way, part of that is machine
learning in deep whatever. But there's
another part, which is algorithms. Because
actually, what comes into your LIDAR
scanner is on the order of like thousands
of points and some minuscule fraction of
time. And time complexity of your learning
algorithm actually is really critical to
get right. And something that there are a
lot of open problems right now because it's
really not compatible with the hardware
architecture that these cars often use. We
also look at more abstract geometry
problems, like if I give you data, can I
find a geometric structure? So a classic
example of natural language processing,
where we use words like near and far.
In terms of semantics and meaning all the
time, the question is, can we actually
find an embedding of our word data into a
geometric space to facilitate the kind of
statistical algorithms that we care about?
And of course, we apply geometry to
lots of practical problems. Everything from
meshing and scientific computing, which I
think is sort of a classic one. In fact, I
think we're the first group that sort of
enumerated all the cool things that may
happen to hexahedral meshes, which is the
sort of bottom figure here. Because there's
some fun things to look at there. To other
practical problems like taking a, you know,
Eric took a zebra and folded it. We can
take a zebra and move its texture onto a
cat or a pig, or actually off the side of
the screen. But if we download the paper,
it's also a 3D scan of one of my gratitude.
So in any event, in my five minutes
remaining here, I thought I'd dig into
a little bit of detail of two or maybe one
application, depending on
when Jason and Eric get bored.
But essentially, my message for you guys
is, of course, you know, I'm not really a
central CS theory group member here at MIT.
But unfortunately for you guys, 6 .006 is
unavoidable. Even if you want to go into
deep learning, statistics, whatever, data
science, you're going to encounter the
material that you've seen in this course.
And in fact, it's really the bread and
butter of just about everything everybody
does here in this data center. So I thought
I'd give you two quick examples, one of
which is my teaching, one from my research.
So if you continue with me next fall,
we'll teach 6 .837, which is the Intro to
Computer Graphics course. One thing that's
always amazing to students is these
algorithms that produce these beautiful
images can fit in about 10, 20 lines of
code. So really, this is totally facetious,
because if you want those beautiful images
and you use those 20 lines of code, you'll
be waiting until the universe to actually
compute these things. But in any event, one
nice one for rendering, so drawing a bunch
of shapes in a tree, something called ray
casting, or its better known cousin,
ray tracing. Typically, the difference is
whether your rays can bounce off of the
surface and have a secondary thing. Right.
So here's the ray casting algorithm. Let's
say I have a scene built out of spheres and
cubes. I'm going to have a for loop over
every pixel on the computer screen. For
every pixel, I've got to discover what
color that should be. So I shoot a ray from
my eyeball, and find the first object that
it runs into. It's not so hard to intersect
a line in a sphere or a line in a cube. So
what is that algorithm? Well, I've given it
to you on the screen here. Not too bad to
think about. And I think you guys are all
extremely well equipped to analyze
the runtime of this, which is roughly the
number of pixels times the number of
objects. Right. Because for every pixel,
I've got to decide what object the ray out
of my eyeball hits first. So I need a for
loop over every object. Make sense? Cool.
So let's look at sort of a basic rendering
problem. In fact, Eric already secretly
snuck this one in here. So there's a very
famous 3D model called the Stanford bunny.
The Stanford bunny is actually a great
example of a simplicial complex. It is,
in fact, a manifold 1 triangulated surface.
Actually, I'm not sure it's manifold in its
original form. But usually it is. And this
innocent looking, extremely famous
3D model is actually quite pernicious.
So 69 ,000 triangles. And if I want a
1080p, like a high def rendering of my
triangle, then of course there's 2 million
pixels on the screen. So if we look at our
big O expression, roughly our computation
time scales like the product of those two
big numbers. So just to render this ugly
gray bunny takes me a pretty large amount
of time. And in fact, by the way, the bunny
is like this famous test case in computer
graphics. So if you take my class, you'll
be rendering bunnies all day. The reality
is we don't want just like gray flat
shaded bunnies. We want bunnies that are
transparent and reflecting stuff. And
I shoot my bunny with a bullet and it
shatters into a million pieces and all
these cool things. So of course, that ray
casting algorithm in each one of these new
graphics features I add only adds to the
time complexity of the technique that I
implement. So pretty quickly, and indeed,
if you write your own ray tracer at home,
which I strongly encourage you to do, what
you'll discover is
that it's hella slow.
So what is our way out of this? Well, if
you take A37, you'll see that our way out
of these problems in graphics is data
structures and algorithms. It's completely
unavoidable. So for instance, obviously
we spent quite a bit of time in this course
talking about AVL trees. In A37, we'll
spend a big chunk of our course talking
about space partitioning trees. So here, I
actually forgot what kind of tree this is.
I think it's a KD tree. Doesn't matter. In
any event, one thing I could do is take all
the triangles of my bunny and I could put
the entire bunny in a giant cube with the
property that the cube is outside the
bunny. Let's say I cast a ray and the ray
doesn't touch the cube. Can the ray touch
the bunny? No, right? Zing's ray pass it.
So suddenly, I just save myself a lot of
computation time. I don't have to iterate
over all the triangles inside of the bunny
to see whether they hit the ray or not
because I already convinced myself by this
conservative test that I didn't hit even
the bounding box of the whole bunny. Yeah?
Well, that's sort of a nice order one speed
up, but depending on how big the bunny is
relative to the size of my rendered image,
that might not be a super useful efficiency
test. But of course, what could I do? I
could take the box containing the bunny,
I could slice it in half, and I would say,
does my ray hit the front or the back of
the bunny? Or maybe both. That's where
things get annoying. And so on. So now
you have this nice recursive tree structure
where I keep taking the box containing my
bunny and chopping it in half and placing,
in some sense, usually the triangles, maybe
not the leaves of my tree, but abstractly
that's probably good enough. And you get
a structure like what you see on the screen
here. And why should you do that? Well,
remember it takes sort of PN time to render
my image of my bunny normally. Well,
now the picture is actually misleadingly
suggestive. But you might think that maybe
it takes roughly, remember, that is the
number of objects in my scene, P log N time
to render my bunny now, because I can kind
of traverse this tree of objects in my
scene. Of course, notice I put a question
mark here. And the devil's in the details
here. In fact, I think computer graphics
people often believe that the rendering
algorithm takes P log N time. That's often
not possible. Although, kind of there's
an interesting question, which is that the
heuristics they use for building these
sorts of trees often do on average give
them log N time. And so there's something
about their data that's making this problem
easier than it might seem. So we'll
dig into that a little bit in the graphics
class. Of course, we're not going to prove
as many bounds as we might in a theory
course. But we're certainly building on the
intuition that you've seen in this class
to build up practical data structures. And
these data structures appear everywhere in
computer graphics. So for instance,
directed acyclic graphs appear all over the
place in computer graphics literature to
describe 3D scenes. So for example, this
classroom, it's a stark reminder of why we
need DAGs in computer graphics, because we
have all of these empty seats here. And
they're all copies of one another. So would
it make sense for me to store however
many, like 100 3D models of the same chair?
Probably not. So instead, what do I do? I
store one instance of a chair and then some
instructions on how to tile it into my
entire scene. So one way that I can do that
is to think of there being a node in a
graph which knows how to draw one node. And
now I can have a bunch of different nodes
in my scene for all the instances of the
chair that store a different transformation
for each one. So if you think about the
graph structure here, each of those nodes
is going to point into the same 3D model of
the chair for rendering. And that makes
a directed acyclic graph structure called a
scene graph, which we'll spend quite a
bit of time talking about in 8 .37, how to
traverse and track all that good stuff.
And there are lots of different models of
computation in that universe as well. Your
graphics card is a very specific kind of
parallel processor that's kind of like
Lucille Ball on the conveyor belt, you
know, hammering at the same object over
and over again. But if you ask it to do
anything other than one thing, it knows
how to do it to a bunch of data at a time,
then all of your computation grinds to
a halt. This is called single instruction
multiple data parallelism, SIMD. Numerical
algorithms matter a lot for things like
fluid simulation. And approximation
algorithms are quite critical too. In
computer graphics, the complexity is
kind of interesting because of course your
eyeball is sensitive to about 29 .97 frames
per second worth of material. You can
choose that time to do like really well
rendering one object, but then you take out
of the time rendering something else. So
there's kind of an interesting conservation
law that you have to balance when you
solve these kinds of problems, which is an
interesting balance now between like
complexity and runtime of your algorithm
and perception. Like what things can you
get away with when you draw a scene? And
maybe like I can do tons of extra
computation to get that extra shadow, but
it's just not worth it. So I'll quickly
sketch out another completely different
application of the material that we've
covered in 6 .006 for my own research.
Again, just like Eric, I guess in a funny
way, both of our groups I think are kind of
broad in terms of subject and material.
Rather than some of our colleagues have
like really laser focus on one topic or
another. Another research area that I sort
of backed into is the area of political
redistricting. This is relevant in the
United States. Recently I've made some
great proposals about other countries,
which is really interesting how they do
this stuff. So in the US, when we vote for
people in Congress, by the way, not
necessarily for presidents, which is a
common misconception, but certainly
for Congress, your state gets divided into
little regions, each of which elects one
member of the House. And there's sort of a
subtle problem if you're not used
to thinking about it, or one that's like
staring you in the face and screaming
depending on how often you read the news in
politics, which is an issue called
gerrymandering, where your legislature
draws the lines for what area on the map
elects a member of Congress. And depending
on how you draw the lines, you can engineer
different results for who's likely to get
elected. So for instance, maybe there's
some minority, I can cluster them all
together into one voting district, then
they'll only get the opportunity to elect
one person. But maybe if I divide the space
where they live into two, I could manage
to engineer two districts with a high
probability of electing somebody with their
political interests in mind. So it turns
out that political redistricting in a broad
sense is a great problem computationally,
even if you're a totally heartless
theorist, there's some really fun problems
here. So for example, the state of Iowa, we
all pick on Iowa, because it has a unique
law, which is that your districts have to
be built out of counties, which are much
larger than the typical census unit, so
computationally it's easier. But even
in Iowa, which is a giant grid, with the
exception of one shift in the middle, which
is fascinating to me. I know I'm blowing
up time. This is a fun fact. Literally,
people were making the map of Iowa, and
they worked from the bottom up and the top
down, and it meets in the middle, and their
grids were shifted, and now we're stuck
with that. And it has an interesting effect
on the topology of your graph, because
it looks like there's two periods, but then
there's triangles in the middle. But in
any event, even though there's only 99
counties and four districts, there's
approximately quintillions of possible ways
you could divide that state into four
contiguous districts that satisfy the rules
as they were, at least if you read them
kind of literally in the law. So it seems
like computers are useful, but
unfortunately, it's a little subtle how. So
for instance, there's no single best
districting plan out there. I can't think
of a single state with a lot of districts,
but I can think of a law that gives you an
objective function, similar to whatever
cute characters that we've had in 6706.
They often have very clear objectives
in life, but unfortunately, redistricting,
that's very rarely the case. You have to
balance connectivity, population balance,
compactness, all
these different things.
Reality check number two is that even
if somebody did give you an objective
function, for just about any interesting
objective function, it's very obvious that
generating the best possible districting
plan is NP -hard. And by the way, it
doesn't even matter, because the law
doesn't say that computers have to draw the
best district. So even if P equals NP,
you really could extract the best possible
districting plan using an algorithm. It
doesn't mean you have to use it, at least
the way the law is written now.
Interestingly, this is not true in certain
parts of Mexico, where they actually make
you compare your districting plan against
the computer -generated one, which
is philosophically really interesting,
although in practice, it doesn't work
terribly. Right, so our research has
studied analysis of districting plans
instead. So instead of writing a piece of
software that takes in your state,
draws your districts, and then you're done,
instead, we ask statistical questions
about, I propose a districting plan, and
what does it look like relative to the
space of the possibilities? So that, of
course, begs the question of, what are the
possibilities? So these are like connected
graph partitions, meaning you have a graph,
and now you take the vertices and you
cluster them together in a way that you
can see where they're connected to one
another. The one thing that we all
agree on, actually, philosophically, it's
questionable why, is that you should be
able to start at any point in your district
and walk to any other one without leaving.
These days, with the internet, it's not
clear that that's actually the best
criterion, but that's a law that I think is
never going to get
passed in the near future.
So anyway, I think I'm out of time, so I
don't think I'll walk you guys through the
theory here. Maybe
I'll leave it in the slides.
So here's some proof that can show that
at least the very simplest thing you might
think of for analyzing your districting
plan, which is to say, you propose a plan,
and now I want your plan to be at least as
good under some axis as to randomly draw on
one from the space of all possible
connected partitions, all possible ways I
could draw the lines. Well, then it might
be useful to have a piece of software that
could just randomly draw such a thing. So
in other words, to draw something where the
probability of any one partition is one
over the number of partitions. This seems
innocent. In fact, actually, there's a
number of papers that claim to do things
like this. But it turns out that it's
computationally difficult, assuming that
you believe that p doesn't equal np. So
I'll maybe leave some suggestive pictures
in the slides that we can, if you guys
text me or if we have a professor -student
chat, I'm happy to sketch it out to you
then. There's a very nice, easy proof that
reduces this to Hamiltonian cycle and shows
you that maybe you shouldn't trust these
schools as much as they're argued about
literally in the Supreme Court a couple
months ago. By the way, it was pretty fun.
Our expert report was referenced in the
dissent of the case last summer. And when
you read the discussion, you can see the
judges trying to talk their way around
complexity. And it's an interesting, if
somewhat dry, read. So in any event, that's
just the starting point for our research,
which says that, of course, these sampling
problems are really hard. And the question
is, well, what can you do? Like, do you
throw the baby out with bathwater or not?
But the real message here is, of course,
that this course is unavoidable. Even in
these extremely applied problems showing
up in court cases or on your graphics card,
you still, complexity and algorithms
and data shift are going to come back into
play. So with that, I'll invite our other
two inspectors up here for our final
farewell, suitably distance ourselves.
So algorithms are everywhere. I hope you
enjoyed this class. It's been a lot of fun
teaching you and having you as students,
even though you're not physically in the
room, we still feel your presence and look
forward to seeing you all soon. Thanks for
being a part of this fun thing. I want to
thank our two co -instructors for an
awesome time this semester. It's been a lot
of fun teaching to you guys. Thanks for
spending 006 with us this term. Yeah, thank
you. Hopefully we'll see
you again soon. Bye. Bye.